Finding Aid for Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences (University of Michigan) records, 1945-2002.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences (University of Michigan) records 1945-2002
University of Michigan. Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences.
A unit of the University of Michigan's Institute of Science and Technology which conducts and sponsors interdisciplinary studies of fresh water lake ecology. It is the successor to the Great Lakes Research Institute and the Great Lakes Research Division of the University of Michigan. Primarily research data, analysis, and reports on two major studies: the Coherent Area Study of Lake Michigan, 1963-1971, and the Donald C. Cook Nuclear Power Plant Studies, 1967-1983.
93813 Bimu 2
42.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences, Donor no. 5394, through Steve Schneider, June 1988, and Nov. 1990.
The collection is open for research.
The Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences (CGLAS) is the successor to the Great Lakes Research Institute (GLRI), the Great Lakes Research Division (GLRD) and the Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center (GLMWC). The mission of each was the "encouragement and integration of studies of the physical, chemical, biological and other aspects of the Great Lakes and related areas." It has sponsored both basic and applied research, published numerous research reports in its "Special Reports" series, and sponsored conferences on the Great Lakes. Though theoretically interested in all the Great Lakes, the center's studies have focused on lakes Michigan, Huron and Superior.
The Great Lakes Research Institute was established by a group of University of Michigan professors and chartered by the Board of Regents in 1945 as part of the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies. By 1953 it had initiated a broad range of studies, the aims of which were: to increase knowledge of the processes and phenomena occurring in large lakes, to determine the characteristics of the Great Lakes as a natural resource so that these could be effectively used and managed, to implement the university's educational goals related to this basic research, and to establish cooperative research programs with other universities and government agencies. The GLRI was governed by a Council of faculty members. David C. Chandler was named director of the Institute in 1953 and later chairman of the council.
The GLRI was reorganized in 1960 and became the Great Lakes Research Division of the University of Michigan Institute of Science and Technology (IST). A further reorganization within IST in 1974 placed the GLRD in the newly created Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center. The Center brought together a number of institutes and programs dealing with the Great Lakes including the Great Lakes Management Program, the Coastal Zone Laboratory, and the Sea-Grant Program, as well as the operation of the university's research vessels. Alfred Beeton was named director of the Center in 1975, succeeding Chandler. In a further reorganization in 1989, GLRD and GLMWC became the Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences, a division of the Institute of Science and Technology. Theodore C. Moore was named director of the Center in 1990.
The CGLAS and its predecessors have operated, or had at their disposal, a number of research vessels. These have included the Inland Seas, Mysis, Naiad, Halcyon, and Highland Lassie. The GLRD also used the General Dynamics submarine Starr II for several research projects in 1967. The staff of CGLAS has included full-time research scientists and faculty members who had joint or partial appointments in academic departments. CGLAS staff have conducted independent research and also worked on contracted projects for corporations and government agencies.
Summary Contents List
Historical Information, 1945-1995 (boxes 1, 38)
Coherent Area Study, 1961-1973
Background and Summary Files (box 1)
Water Temperature Studies (boxes 1-2, 7-10)
Bathythermograph and other logs, (boxes 1-2)
Bathythermograph Slides (boxes 5-9)
Bathythermograph Photos (box 10)
Biological Studies (boxes 2-4)
Chemical Studies (boxes 4-5)
Meteorological Studies (boxes 5, 11-13)
Wind and Current Studies (boxes 5-6)
Standards and Procedures (box 6)
Miscellaneous CAS Files (box 6)
Audio Tapes (box 6)
Photographs and Film (box 6)
Ship's Logs and Operations, 1961-2002
Ship's Logs (Deck Logs), 1961-2000 (boxes 14-16, 33, 43)
Chief Scientist's Log, 1961-1979 (boxes 16-17)
Chronological Files, 1966-2002 (boxes 38-40)
(See also Topical Files under ship names (boxes 40-41))
Donald C. Cook Nuclear Power Plant Studies, 1967-1984
Limnological Studies, 1967-1984 (boxes 18, 24)
Phytoplankton Studies data (box 19)
Biological Studies (box 20)
Environmental Impact Statement and Other Reports, 1973-1983
Environmental Technical Specifications (box 20)
Licensing Hearings (box 20)
Environmental Operating Reports, 1974-1983 (box 21)
Environmental Regulatory Guidelines (box 22)
Ice Studies
"Shore Ice Structures at Cook Nuclear Plant" (box 22)
Ice Slides and Logbooks (boxes 25-32)
Chronological Files, 1969-1979 (box 36)
Lake Michigan Ice Study (boxes 22-23)
John C. Ayers Research Files, 1954-1973 (box 24)
Administration, 1971-1998 (boxes 34-36)
Grants, 1960-1980 (boxes 36-38)
Topical files, 1960-2002 (boxes 40-42)
Visual materials (box 42)
The records in this collection are largely research files from the period when John C. Ayers was director of research for the Great Lakes Research Division. The bulk of the records document two large research projects: the Coherent Area Study, 1963-1971, and Donald C. Cook Nuclear Power Plant Studies, 1967-1983. There is also documentation of several smaller research projects. The research files include reports, field and laboratory data, and a variety of logs documenting data collection. The collection has few if any administrative records of the GLRD or its successors.
The records are arranged in ten series: Historical Information, Coherent Area Study, Ship's Logs, Donald C. Cook Power Plant Studies, Lake Michigan Ice Studies, John C. Ayers Research Files, Administration, Grants, Topical files, and Visual materials. Because the records contain a variety of formats, including slides, fan-fold computer printouts, and outsize volumes, some subgroups and series are split between ranges of box numbers. The summary contents list provides an overview of the physical arrangement of the records.
Subjects:
Donald C. Cook Nuclear Power Plant.; Environmental impact statements.; Environmental protection--Michigan.; Grand Traverse Bay (Mich.); Great Lakes Region--Research.; Limnology--Great Lakes.; Michigan, Lake.; Nuclear power plants--Environmental aspects--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Center for Great Lakes and Aquatic Sciences.
Contributors:
Ayers, John C. (John Carr), 1912-; University of Michigan. Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center.; University of Michigan. Great Lakes Research Division.; University of Michigan. Great Lakes Research Institute.; West Michigan Environmental Action Council.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Historical Information
  The Historical Information series consists of photocopies of four publications from GLRD's "Special Reports" series. "The Great Lakes and the University of Michigan", 1953, "The Great Lakes and Michigan," 1953, and "Great Lakes Research Institute: Organization, Objectives and Programs", 1956, describe some of the early research projects of the GLRI. "Project Submich", 1968, is a report on GLRD's experiments using the research submarine "Star II" in 1966. Also included here is a 1988 bibliography of the "Special Report" publications. (This collection includes only the three reports listed above and the multi-part report on the Donald C. Cook Nuclear Plant described below. Copies of other reports may be available at CGLAS.)
  - "Special Reports" series
    - "The Great Lakes and the University of Michigan", Special Report #1 1953 (Box 1)
    - "The Great Lakes and Michigan" Special Report #3 1955 (Box 1)
    - "Great Lakes Research Institute: Organization, Objectives and Programs", in Special Report #4, "Great Lakes Programs and Problems" 1956 (Box 1)
    - "Project Submich", Special Report #33 1968 (Box 1)
    - Bibliography of Special Report series 1988 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1945-1995
    - Anchors 2000 (Box 38)
    - Field Plans 1954-1956 (Box 38)
    - Great Lakes Research Institute Cruise Poster 1955 (Box 38)
    - News Stories 1963-1975 (Box 38)
    - Organization of Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center 1974 (Box 38)
    - Organization of Great Lakes Research Division 1960 (Box 38)
    - Organization of Great Lakes Research Institute 1945 (Box 38)
    - Printed Material 1968-2002 (Box 38)
    - Proposals for Research Programs 1945-1953 (Box 38)
    - Research Projects 1953 (Box 38)
    - Some Great Lakes People and Platforms 1995 (Box 38)
    - Upper Great Lakes Conference 1953 (Box 38)
- Coherent Area Study 1963-1971
  The Coherent Area Study (CAS) was an interdisciplinary study of the biology, chemistry, geology, meteorology, and physical limnology of Lake Michigan. Funded by the U.S. Public Health Service, CAS aimed at gathering scientific information on the behavior of large lakes, particularly the process of and factors leading to eutrophication. The study was conducted in two phases, 1963-1967 and 1967-1971, under the direction of John Ayers, professor of oceanography and GLRD research scientist. Data for the study was gathered at monitoring stations and from research vessel cruises. Records in this series include field and laboratory data, analysis and reports, and a variety of research vessel logs.
  The arrangement of the CAS series begins with a series of background and summary files. These are followed by series for each of the major areas of scientific study: water temperature, biological, chemical, climatological, meteorological, and wind current studies. There are small series of audiotapes and photographs and films.
  Arranged in a separate series are two series of ship's logs which relate in part to the Comprehensive Area Study. The ship's logs series and chief scientist's logs series, described below, cover research vessel cruises for CAS as well as earlier and later studies. Researchers should note the interrelationships among these records, particularly the various field data logs and the ship's logs. It may be necessary to consult the ship's logs to determine precisely where in the lake and under what conditions readings or samples were taken.
  - Background and Summary Files
    The Background and Summary Files subseries includes the grant renewal application, a summary report on the first phase of the study, bibliographies, and several historical data files The Grant Renewal Application, 1966, provides summary information on the preliminary findings of the 1963-1967 phase of the project and describes the studies to be carried out in the second phase. The draft Supplemental Progress Report, Oct. 1966 provides an outline of CAS work completed to date.
    Bibliographies consists of abstracts of previous publications and research on Lake Michigan. Historical Data is time-series data on water temperature, wind, and meteorological conditions from cities around Lake Michigan. Some series were apparently compiled by Ayers, others were provided by local agents such as city water filtration plants. It was part of a "weather library" created by Ayers and GLRD. The Summaries of Data Collecting Logs of Research Vessel Cruises provide summaries of the type, extent, and location for data collected on GLRD research vessel cruises, 1962-1967.
    - Grant Renewal Proposal 1966 (Box 1)
    - Supplemental Progress Report 1966 (Box 1)
    - Bibliographies and Weather Library Index (Box 1)
    - Historical Data (Water temperature, wind, meteorological, from "weather library") (Box 1)
    - Summaries of Data Collecting Logs of Research Vessel Cruises (Box 1)
  - Water Temperature Studies
    The Water Temperature Studies subseries consists of several files relating to bathythermograph recordings and other water temperature logs. A bathythermograph is a device which is lowered into the lake to record changes in water temperature as a function of depth. The instrument etches a line on a coated glass slide. The slide is then projected and photographed against a graph for interpretation.
    Files include: Station Locations, a list of fixed stations from which recordings were made; Bathythermograph Logs, a record of the date, time, location, and other information for observations made from research vessels; Bathythermograph Glass Slides and Bathythermograph Photographs of some slides. The bathythermograph logs, slides, and photographs are arranged by year and research vessel. Other logs record water temperatures at fixed stations in Lake Michigan and Lake Huron. The Airborne Radiant Thermograph file is data from an experimental system using an ASWEPS (Anti-submarine Warfare Environmental Predictions Services) Oceanographic research plane to measure lake surface water temperature.
    - Bathythermograph Operating Instructions (Box 1)
    - Bathythermograph Station Locations (Box 1)
    - Bathythermograph Log Sheets
      - 1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962 (Box 1)
      - 1963, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - 1964 (Box 1)
      - 1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966 (Box 1)
      - 1967 (Box 1)
      - 1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969 (Box 1)
    - Bathythermograph Slides
      - Inland Seas Cruises
        - 1962 # 1-430 (Box 7)
        - 1963 # 431-857 (Box 7)
        - 1964 # 858-1083 (Box 7)
        - 1965 #1084-1363 (Box 7)
        - 1966 #1364-1650 (Box 7)
        - 1967 #1651-1932 (Box 7)
        - 1968 #1933-2191 (Box 7)
        - 1969 #2192-2359 (Box 8)
        - 1970 #2368-2766 (Box 8)
        - 1971 # 2767-2988 (Box 8)
        - 1972 # 2989-3452 (Box 8)
        - 1973 #3453-3495 (Box 8)
      - Mysis Cruises
        - 1962 (Box 8)
        - 1963 (Box 8)
        - 1964 (Box 8)
        - 1965 # 1-172 (Box 8)
        - 1966 # 173-320 (Box 8)
        - 1967 # 321-423 (Box 8)
      - Naiad Cruises 1964 (Box 8)
      - Lassie Cruises 1964 (Box 8)
      - Woodbine Cruises 1965 (Box 8)
      - Lady Maggie Cruises 1961 (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous Bathythermograph Slides
        - 1954-1957 (Box 9)
        - Northern Lake Michigan (Box 9)
        - Southern Lake Michigan (Box 9)
        - Environmental Protection Agency (Box 9)
    - Bathythermograph Photos (Box 10)
    - Water Temperature Log
      - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - 1965 (graphs) (Box 2)
      - 1965-1966 Lake Huron, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1966 (Box 2)
    - Surface Temperature Charts 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Airborne Radiant Thermograph (ART) Data
      - "Coyote" Flight Data
        - October 1966 (Box 2)
        - 1967 (Box 2)
      - "Navoceano" Flight Data 1967 (Box 2)
  - Biological Studies
    The Biological Studies subseries consists primarily of field and laboratory data from algae, benthos, and plankton studies. The Algae Counts record the level of algae present in samples from fixed reference stations. The Benthos Counts and Benthos Statistics record the presence of organisms living on or in the lake bottom. The Benthos Counts are time-series data recording the presence of eight principal organisms at individual observation stations or from research vessel voyages. They are arranged by date and observation point. The Benthos Statistics aggregate the Count data by type of organism. The Benthos Summaries and Benthos Weights provide some analysis of the counts and statistics. The Phytoplankton and Zooplankton files provide data and some analysis of the type of plankton present in lake water samples. The Biological Log Sheets provide a chronological record of the time, location, and conditions under which the samples for biological analysis were taken.
    - Algae Count and Notes 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Benthos Count, data sheets
      - 1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965 (Box 2)
      - 1966 (Box 2)
      - 1967 (Box 2)
    - Benthos Count Statistics
      - 1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965 (Box 3)
      - 1966 (Box 3)
    - Benthos Count Summaries 1964-1966 (Box 3)
    - Benthos Weights 1964-1966 (Box 3)
    - Phytoplankton 1964-1966 (Box 3)
    - Plankton, Methods and Sample Data 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - Zooplankton Notes (Box 3)
    - Biological Log Sheets
      - 1964
        - April-July (Box 3)
        - August-Nov (Box 3)
      - 1965
        - March-July (Box 3)
        - July-Sept (Box 3)
        - September-Nov (Box 3)
      - 1966
        - March-June (Box 3)
        - June-November, 1966 (Box 3)
        - Power Plant Pomar Stations (Box 3)
      - January-June, 1967 (Box 3)
      - July-November, 1967 (Box 4)
      - 1968 (Box 4)
    - Data Sheets
      - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1964 (Box 4)
      - 1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1966 (Box 4)
      - 1967 (Box 4)
  - Chemical Studies
    The Chemical Studies subseries includes several files of field and laboratory data on chemical analysis of lake water samples.
    - Composite Reference Station Data (Box 4)
    - Conductivity, Sulfate, Sodium (Box 4)
    - Dissolved Organics 1964-1965 (Box 4)
    - Lake Chemistry [Atlas Study], 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Phosphorous 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - River Sampling Log 1962, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Water Analysis Data
      - 1962 (Box 4)
      - 1964 (Box 5)
      - 1965 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Papers on Water Analysis (Box 5)
  - Meteorological Studies
    The Meteorological Studies subseries, 1962-1967, includes a file of historical climatological data on the Great Lakes region as well as contemporary meteorological data from land stations and research vessel cruises. These contain data on daily temperature, wind, cloud, and precipitation conditions. Also included here are three folders of weather observations from Lake Michigan car ferry vessels, 1967-1970. The 641 Meteorological Data file consists of computer printouts of meteorological data recorded by the 641 instrument. It includes date and time of reading, air and water temperature, dew point, and locational information such as ship speed and direction. It is arranged by vessel and date. Meteorological Data Analysis file is computer printouts of program runs analyzing data from the 641 recorder.
    - Climatologic Data (Historical) (Box 5)
    - Cumulative Degree Days (Box 5)
    - Logs and Charts
      - 1962 (Box 5)
      - 1964 (Box 5)
      - 1964 (Wiresonde record and wind maps) (Box 5)
      - 1968 (Box 5)
    - Lake Michigan Storm Data
      - 1962-1963 (Box 5)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Weather Observations, Car Ferry Logs
      - "City of Green Bay" 1967-1968 (Box 5)
      - "S.S. Madison" 1969-1980 (Box 5)
      - "City of Midland" 1968-1970 (Box 5)
    - Meteorological Data Recorder, Operation and Codes (Box 11)
    - 641 Recorder Data (Meteorological data recorded on research cruises, computer printouts)
      - Inland Seas
        - 1964
          - July 27-September 15 (Box 11)
          - September 29-November 10 (Box 11)
        - 1965
          - May 15-August 21 (Box 11)
          - September 7-Nov (Box 11)
        - 1966
          - March 21-May (Box 11)
          - June 1- (Box 11)
          - Fall (Box 11)
        - 1967
          - June 12- (Box 12)
          - July 27- (Box 12)
      - Mysis
        - 1965
          - Summer (Box 12)
          - Fall (Box 12)
        - 1966
          - Spring (Box 12)
          - Summer (Box 12)
          - Fall (Box 12)
    - Meteorological Data Recorder Log 1962, 1966, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Meteorological Data Analysis
    - Computer printouts (Box 13)
  - Wind and Current Studies 1961-1967
    The Wind and Current Studies subseries, 1961-1967, contains data and reports on a number of studies conducted by Vincent Noble prior to and in conjunction with the Coherent Area Study.
    - Wind Log October, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Wind Log, Manitou Island 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - Logs and Charts, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Vertical Current Structures in Lake Michigan (Box 6)
    - Decay of Wind Driven Currents (Box 6)
    - Plotted Spectra Wave Data (Box 6)
    - Dynamic Height Current Charts (Box 6)
    - Hydrographic Log Sheets
      - Inland Seas 1962-1963 (Box 6)
      - Mysis 1963 (Box 6)
  - Standards and Procedures
    The Standards and Procedures subseries, ca. 1962-1967, contains information on the standards and procedures for data gathering and analysis for the various studies and experiments that were part of the Coherent Area Study.
    - circa 1961-1967, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous CAS Files
    - Great Lakes Basin Population Data (Box 6)
    - Boat and Filtration Plant Comparison Data (Plankton?) (Box 6)
    - Sewage Treatment Facilities (Box 6)
  - Audio Tapes
    Audiotapes consists of ten cassettes of "audio logs" of dives of the research submarine "Star II" in Lake Michigan in 1967. Research scientists recorded observations on plankton, turbidity, ambient light, water temperature and various instrument readings as the vessel submerged at various points in Lake Michigan. There is also a tape of a 1967 WUOM broadcast about the GLRD sponsored Star II research.
    - Star II Submarine Operation 1967, 10 audiocassettes (Box 6)
    - Star II-A Special Report, WUOM broadcast June 29, 1967, 5" reel, 7.5 ips, 14 min. (Box 6)
  - Photographs and Film circa 1954-1968 (Box 6)
    The Photographs and Film subseries, ca. 1954- ca. 1968 (2 folders) contains photos of GLRD research vessel crews and scientists at work and a portrait of John C. Ayers. There is one short (50 ft.) 16mm film of Professor Hough's 1965 class on a field trip on board one of the research vessels.
- Ship's Logs and Operations 1955-2002
  The Ship's Logs series, 1957-1984, includes two types of logs: Ship's Logs and Chief Scientist's Logs. Ship's Logs (some are titled "deck logs") are daily logs of research vessel voyages recording ship locations, destinations, and activities. The series covers research cruises associated with Coherent Area Study as well as the Cook Nuclear Plant studies and other research projects. It includes subseries for the primary UM research vessels, Inland Seas, 1962-1973 and Mysis, 1963-1984, as well as the Highland Lassie II, 1964-1965, Lady Maggie, 1961, Maple, 1973, and Laurentian, 1979-1984. Each subseries is arranged chronologically. For the Inland Seas there are sometimes both "rough logs", originals kept by the captain and "smooth logs", transcribed copies. There are occasional differences and some gaps in each of the Inland Seas subseries.
  - Ship's Logs (Deck Logs)
    - Inland Seas 1962-1973 (Box 14)
    - Laurentian 1974-1976 (Box 14)
    - Laurentian 1974-1976 (Box 43)
    - Maple 1973 (Box 14)
    - Mysis
      - September 1963-November 1968 (Box 15)
        (narrative ship's log, photocopy)
      - 1963-1977 (Box 15)
      - 1978-1984 (Box 16)
    - Highland Lassie II 1964-1965 (Box 16)
    - Lady Maggie 1961 (Box 16)
  - Ship's Logs (Deck Logs) (outsized volumes, mainly "smooth" logs)
    - Inland Seas
      - June 1963-July 1967, 21 volumes (Box 33)
      - May 1972-June 1973, 1 volumes (Box 33)
    - Maple August 1973-October 1973 (Box 33)
      (in last Inland Seas volume.)
    - Laurentian
      - 1979-2000, 3 volumes (Box 43)
  - Chief Scientist's Log
    The Chief Scientist's Logs, 1957-1979, were kept by the head research scientist on board each research vessel. They are a daily log of experimental activity; recording such information as location where samples were taken, where recording devices were turned on, meteorological conditions during experiments, etc. They are arranged by vessel and thereunder chronologically.
    - Inland Seas 1962, 1964-1971, 1973, 10 volumes in 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Laurentian 1974-1979, 5 volumes (Box 33)